<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Literæ illustr. Domini Fagel, Hollandiæ pensionarii, ad Dominum Jacobum Steuart, advocatu[m], hoc eodem quo jam prodeunt idiomate exaratæ : in quibus quæ sit Serenissimorum Principum Auriacorum de Testæ Legumque Pœnalium contra pontificios in Britannia lrtarum [sic] abolitione sententia declaratur A letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel, pensioner of Holland, to Mr. James Stewart, advocate : giving an account of the Prince and Princess of Orange's thoughts concerning the repeal of the Test and the Penal Laws.</title>
            <title>Letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel, pensioner of Holland, to James Stewart, advocate. Latin &amp; English</title>
            <author>Fagel, Gaspar, 1634-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F92</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R236849</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12711250</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12711250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 353:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Literæ illustr. Domini Fagel, Hollandiæ pensionarii, ad Dominum Jacobum Steuart, advocatu[m], hoc eodem quo jam prodeunt idiomate exaratæ : in quibus quæ sit Serenissimorum Principum Auriacorum de Testæ Legumque Pœnalium contra pontificios in Britannia lrtarum [sic] abolitione sententia declaratur A letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel, pensioner of Holland, to Mr. James Stewart, advocate : giving an account of the Prince and Princess of Orange's thoughts concerning the repeal of the Test and the Penal Laws.</title>
                  <title>Letter writ by Mijn Heer Fagel, pensioner of Holland, to James Stewart, advocate. Latin &amp; English</title>
                  <author>Fagel, Gaspar, 1634-1688.</author>
                  <author>Stewart, James, Sir, 1635-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Parallel Latin and English Texts.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: Novemb. 1687, Gasp. Fagel.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term>Test Act (1673)</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:66097:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>LITERAE ILLUSTR: DOMINI FAGEL, HOLLANDIAE PENSIONARII, AD DOMINUM JACOBUM STEUART Advocatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Hoc codem, quo jam prodeunt, idiomate exaratae. In quibus quae ſit Sereniſſimorum Principum Auriacorum de Teſtae Legumque poenalium contra Pontiſicios in BRITAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA Irtarum abolitione ſententia, declaratur.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Vir Nobiliſſime &amp; Ampliſſime.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Doleo vehementer valetudinem quâ uſus ſum minus proſperâ, cauſam fuiſſe me non potuiſſe citius reſpondere epiſtolis, quibus petis &amp; efflagitas, ut certiorem te facere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim, quid Sereniſſimi <hi>Principes</hi> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiant de Legibus Paenalibus &amp; nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natim de eâ quae vulgô <hi>Teſta</hi> appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur abolendis. Perſuaſiſſimum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas rogo, me hac in re apertiſſimè &amp; abſque omni omnino circuitione recum aucturum, maximè cum ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, literas quas miſiſti <hi>ſciente &amp; approbante Rege</hi> exaratas eſſe. Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate &amp; ſignificate igitur tibi debeo <hi>Sereniſsimos Principes</hi> ſaepius <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66097:2"/>&amp; quidem ipſi Domino Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni d' Abbiville Ablegato Majeſtatis ſuae ad Foederati Belgii Ordines Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nario,</hi> &amp; etiam nunc in ea eſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiâ;</p>
            <p>Neminem <hi>Chriſtianorum perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendum</hi> aut moleſtiis afficiendum ob id tantùm, quod à <hi>publica</hi> aut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominante, uti loqui amant, <hi>religione diſſentiat,</hi> &amp; omnino pati poſſe quod <hi>Pontificiis</hi> in Anglia Scotia, Hyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia permittatur profiteri religionem ſuam ea cum libertate, eoque modo, quibus <hi>in illa harum provinciarum fruuntur,</hi> in quâ quam maximâ gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent indulgentiâ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sereniſsimos</hi> praeterea <hi>Principes</hi> non tantùm non adverſari, ſed quam maximè probare, Eis, quos <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes</hi> nominant, concedi omnimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam libertatem &amp; facultatem reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem ſuam exercendi abſque ullis omnino impedimentis aut obſtacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, ita ut nemo eis eam ob cauſam moleſtus, gravis, iniquus aut incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus eſſe debeat aut poſſit.</p>
            <p>Adhaec <hi>Sereniſsimos Principes,</hi> ſi id majeſtati ſuae placeat, quam libentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè acturos &amp; anniſuros ſedulò, ut ejuſmodi libertas ſtabiliatur &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concuſſa reddatur, imo ſponſuros ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſe libertatem defenſuros, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturos, &amp; <hi>Guarantiâ</hi> (uti loquimur) ſuâ confirmaturos, de qua tu in literis tuis locutus es: Quin &amp; ſi Majeſtas
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66097:2"/>ſua id deſiderat, omnem operam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibituros, ut Leges <hi>Poenales</hi> abrogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ita tamen, ut ea <hi>Legum Capita,</hi> quae <hi>Pontificiis ad Parlamenta</hi> aliaque munera &amp; <hi>Officia publica, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Civium, publici Regiminis, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae, aut Militiae ſpectantia aditum</hi> negant, ſarta tecta maneant, ut &amp; ea capita quae in Securitatem &amp; Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitatem <hi>Religionis Reformatae,</hi> &amp; ne quid in eam Pontificii moliantur, ſancitaſunt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sereniſsimos</hi> autem Principes cum Majeſtate ſuâ non <hi>convenire</hi> neque aſſenſum ſuum praebere poſſe ut <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta</hi> quae dicitur, aut modo laudata Legum poenalium capita abrogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quibus nihil aliud agitur quam ne Pontificii aut ad Parliamenta aut ad praedicta munera aut officia publica vocentur, aut ut ſua Religioni Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matae ſecuritas conſlet, &amp; ne quid ad tranquillitatem ejus turbandam Pontificii moliantur; quoniam ita dicta <hi>Teſta</hi> &amp; ea Legum poenalium pars nullam Pontificiis aut poenam aut mulctam imponunt, ſed aliud ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſtatuunt quam ut ad Parliamenta &amp; praedicta munera &amp; officia publica ii tantum habiles reddantur qui Deo &amp; hominibus coram <hi>declarare &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari poſſunt &amp; volunt ſe eſſe Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae &amp; non Pontificiae Religionis;</hi> Et ut ſedulo provideatur ne Religio Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formata à Pontificiis quicquam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimenti
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66097:3"/>capiat. <hi>Sereniſsimos Principes</hi> cenſuiſſe &amp; adhuc cenſere plura aut ampliora ab iis jure exigi aut expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctari non poſſe: Pontificiis &amp; eorum poſteris hac via in perpetuum conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, ſecuris ne qua deinceps moleſtia perſonis, bonis, aut etiam exercitio <hi>religionis</hi> eorum inferatur; contentos itaque eos eſſe, nec tranquillitatem regni turbare debere, quia non etiam ad <hi>Parliamenta</hi> &amp; alia munera publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca vocantur, &amp; quod non ſimul ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogetur id omne quod iis in Legibus tantum ſecuritatem Religionis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatae ſpectat, &amp; impedimento eſt, ne quid Pontificii in ea turbatum eant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Satisfieri</hi> etiam deſideriis eorum quos <hi>Diſſentientes</hi> nominant, cum in perpetuum eximantur omni metu &amp; ſuſpicione, ne in libero <hi>Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> eorum exercitio unquam aliquid moleſtiae, incommodi aut obſtacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li creari, evenire aut obrepere poſſit.</p>
            <p>Mihi igitur videtur ex hac decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione <hi>Sereniſsimorum Principum</hi> manifeſtum fieri eos nihil minus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo agitare, quàm impedire ut <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentientes</hi> quos nominant à dictis Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus poenalibus liberentur, cum parati ſint omni opera niti ut haec ita conſtituantur &amp; firmentur, nec etiam ullo modo id agere, ut Pontificiis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getur exercitium Religionis eorum,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66097:3"/>modo illud <hi>modeſtè,</hi> &amp; abſque ulla <hi>publica oſtentatione</hi> peragatur.</p>
            <p>Me quidem quod attinet, ſum &amp; fui ſemper alieniſſimus ab iis qui Chriſtianum perſequendum cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint ob eam ſolam cauſam, quod à publica &amp; praedominante, uti ajunt, religione diſſentiat, &amp; ſpero favente Deo eandem mihi in perpetuum fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſententiam. Nam cum lumen quod in cordibus noſtris. Religio ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendit, adſcribendum plane ſit, ut mihi quidem videtur, miſericordiae divinae; noſtrarum partium eſſe arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tror Deo eo nomine gratias agere quam maximas, miſereri ſortis eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. qui etiam nunc errant, que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madmodum Deus noſtri miſertus eſt, &amp; ab eo ardentiſſimis precibus petere, ut errantes in viam reducere velit, nobis ſatagentibus, ut eam iis placide &amp; amice monſtrare poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. Lubens tamen fateor me nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam capere potuiſſe, cuiquam qui exercitio religionis ſuae quietè &amp; ſine ulla moleſtia frui poteſt, &amp; qui ſe Chriſtianum profitetur, fas eſſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cujuſcunque Regni aut Reipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicae turbare aut immutare velle, ut ad munera &amp; honores publicos eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatur, aut ne Religioni publicae &amp; praedominanti, ut ajunt, inconcuſſa maneat ſua vel ſecuritas vel tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitas.</p>
            <p>Video autem <hi>Religionem Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matam</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66097:4"/>Dei Gratia tam in Anglia, Scotia, quam Hybernia eſſe publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, &amp; ut ajunt praedominantem, video leges ibi latas &amp; ſancitas à <hi>Rege &amp; Parliamentis,</hi> id eſt, omni populo, quae ad muniá Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, munera &amp; <hi>officia Publica</hi> eos tantum vocant, qui ſunt &amp; <hi>publicè profitentur &amp; teſtantur ſe eſſe Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Reformatae, &amp; non Pontificiae, &amp; quae cavent conſervationi Religionis Reformatae, &amp; ne quid in eam Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii moliantur, non quod eae Leges ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius quid ſtatuunt in Bona au Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas eorum, qui nolunt profiteri aut te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari ſe non eſſe Pontificios,</hi> ſed quae ſalvis eorum religione, perſona, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, eos tantum non recipiunt ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendam Rempublicam aut alia mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera &amp; honores publicos, quamdiu ex animo ſe eſſe Reformatae &amp; non Pontificiae Religonis, profiteri &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari nequeunt, &amp; quae prohibent, ne quâ reformatos moleſtiâ afficiant, <hi>Sereniſsimis Principibus, uti dixi, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis in id cum Majeſtate ſua eniti, ut ea Legum poenalium capita abrogentur, quae alias poenas vel mulctas indicunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſtat igitur nullam circa abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litionem Legum poenalium ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe differentiam, niſi quod nonnulli Pontificios ad capeſſenda munia, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia &amp; honores publicos recipere, &amp; quicquid de iis Legibus in ſecurita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; tranquillitatem <hi>Reformatae
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66097:4"/>Religionis,</hi> &amp; ne quid in eam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liri poſſit, cautum eſt, abrogatum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint, aliis contra tendentibus, ut ea legum poenalium capita firma &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra, &amp; haec Religionis publicae &amp; praedominantis, ut ajunt, id eſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatae praerogativa immota ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neat.</p>
            <p>Extra omnem dubitandi aleam eſt nullibi dari Regnum, Rempubicam, quinimo corpus aut collegium lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, in quo non reperiantur leges quae inſerviunt ejus ſecuritati &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam eunt illicitis aliorum conatibus, &amp; ſimul praeſcribunt quibus dotibus ornati, cujus conditionis eſſe debeant, qui ad obeunda munia &amp; officia in Regnis, Rebuspublicis aut Collegiis iſtis admittentur, neque injuriam ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam fieri iis quorum nomina ex hac regula non recipiuntur.</p>
            <p>Negari etiam non poteſt inter Reformatam &amp; Pontificiam Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem quam maximum eſſe diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; Pontificios enim non modo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludere Reformatos ab omnibus mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus &amp; officiis publicis, verume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam iis interdicere omne Religionis ſuae exercitium, imo eos quam ac errimè perſequi omnibus in regioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; locis, ubi &amp; quamprimum id tuto &amp; abſquè periculo fieri poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> credunt; atque utinam hoc ipſo, quo vivimus, tempore tam triſtia, tam de ploranda, tam multis in locis hac
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66097:5"/>de re exempla oculis noſtris non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarentur.</p>
            <p>Vellem itaque vel unicam mihi dari rationem, qua Reformatus Deum timens &amp; de Religione ſua ſollicitus moveri poſſit ad diſſolven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das leges cum conſenſu Regum &amp; Parliamentorum conditas, quatenus eae Leges tantum proſpiciunt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati Reformatorum, &amp; repagulis quibuſdam Pontificiorum in illos conatus coercent, nec poenam nec mulctam infligunt, nec aliud exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt quam ne Pontificii regimini aut muneribus publicis admovean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, atque eâ viâ cavere volunt ne Pontificii incrementum eamque ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirant vim &amp; authoritatem, quae Religioni Reformatae for midoloſa &amp; quam maximo detrimento eſſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, quod quotidie evenire videmus, quando qui ad munera &amp; officia pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blica vocantur, aut Pontificiis aut Reformatis plus minus addicti ſunt.</p>
            <p>Et quisquam mihi aut alteri autor foret ad <hi>Principes,</hi> quos Deus tam Illuſtri Nutritiorum Eccleſiae ſuae titulo exornat, inducendos aut pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movendos, ut probarent, laudarent Reformatae Religioni, quinimo quieti &amp; tranquillitati publicae extra omnem controverſiam tam pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſa tam noxia. Neque enim, pace quod flat tuâ, ullus concedere poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, nihil inde, quod tu arbitraris,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66097:5"/>damni Religionem Reſormatam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepturam.</p>
            <p>Fateor vulgo dici Pontificios in Anglia &amp; Scotia non eſſe magno numero, &amp; non niſi exiguam partem munerum &amp; officiorum publico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum penes eos eſſe, (quanquam in Hybernia res plane aliter ſe habet) ſed id mihi largiri neceſſe eſt, ſi nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus, ut dicitur, Pontificiorum eſt tam exiguus, hunc numerum non debere turbare tranquillitatem re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gni maxime cum tam ingens benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium liberam ſcilicet exercendae Religionis ſuae facultatem acciperet: Quod ſi numerus corum ſit major, eum tantò magis metuendum. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimos quidem credo hoc rerum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Pontificios non admodum fore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidos munerum aut officiorum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicorum, neque quicquam in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatos molituros, quod id Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus prohibitum ſciant, &amp; vereantur, ne id quandoque maximum perſonis &amp; bonis eorum diſpendium afferre poſſet; ſed remotis iis repagulis, videbimus eos regimini ad motos, &amp; quam maximam munerum &amp; officiorum publicorum partem ab iis exornari, neque Majeſtati ſuae, ut ut forti eſt animo, integrum erit reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66097:6"/>iis qui quotidie &amp; ſine ulla inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione hoc urgebunt, &amp; ut obtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, conſcientiam &amp; religionem Majeſtatis ſuae appellabunt: quid au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Reformatis hoc legum auxilio deſtitutis ab ejuſmodi Magiſtratu fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret exſpectandum, &amp; quantum emo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumenti Pontificiis, iis Legum vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ſolutis accederet, clarius eſt, quam ut demonſtratione aut proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione egeat.</p>
            <p>In dubium vocare nec debeo nec volo ſinceram Majeſtatis ſuae inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, nec aliud ei eſſe propoſitum, quam ut ſubditi ſui aequo jure &amp; ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quali libertate vivant, agant; verum ratio ipſa &amp; omnium temporum etiam hujus experientia evincunt, impoſſibile eſſe, quod Pontificii &amp; Reformati regimini, muneribus, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis publicis ſimul admoti, placidè &amp; quieté ea adminiſtrabunt, nec al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alteri ſuſpectus ſit, cum in principiis &amp; fundamentis ipſis adeo ſibi invicem oppoſiti &amp; contrarii reperiuntur; nec meo quidem judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio in ulius Regis aut Principis pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate erit, ſimultates &amp; aemulationes inde ſemper repullulaturas tollere.</p>
            <p>Quod autem vereris ne ii quos <hi>Diſſentientes</hi> nominant, eam quam
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66097:6"/>diximus libertatem adipiſcantur per abolitionem legum paenalium, niſi eae in totum, ut &amp; <hi>Teſta</hi> quam appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, abrogentur, maximum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eſſet Infortunium, ſed unicè adſcribendum Pontificiis, qui ſe &amp; poſteros. ſuos legibus paenalibus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictos, &amp; totius populi odio expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitos mallent quam prohiberi, ne quid contra ſecuritatem &amp; traquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem Religionis Reformatae mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liantur, &amp; carere hoc parvo commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ſi quod eſt, quod in adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Reipublicae, &amp; in obeundis muneribus &amp; officiis publicis conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere poſſet, cum tamen haec ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; ubique fuerit, praerogativa publicae &amp; praedominantis, uti ajunt, Religionis. Reformatis certe hi Pontificiorum conatus, tanto magis ſuſpecti &amp; praecavendi eſſent, ſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derint eos adhuc paenalibus legibus obnoxios, id tamen agere, ut <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtas ſua</hi> autor fieret, <hi>velint nolint Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formati,</hi> ne <hi>ſua religioni reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae Legibus jam firmata ſecuritas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet,</hi> &amp; ut <hi>Pontificiis</hi> aditus ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen, munera &amp; officia publica pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teat, quippe quibus tunc auxilii ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſupereſſet, quam quod à magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratu Pontificio expectandum fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66097:7"/>Injuriam ſane maximam Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimis Principibus facerent, qui quid hac in re incommodi eveniret iis aſcriberent, cum animi ſui ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam tam apertè teſtati ſint, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in tantum ipſorum Pontificio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum commodum cedat, idque ob eam ſolam cauſam, quod permoveri non potuerint, ut conſentirent Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus ante latis tam contrariis &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioni reformatae tam periculoſis tam noxiis, qualia ſunt Pontificios ad regimen, ad officia &amp; munera pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blica admittere, &amp; abrogare leges, quae unicè ſecuritati &amp; tranquillitati religionis reformatae, &amp; ne quid in eam Pontificii moliantur, inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viunt.</p>
            <p>Scribis Pontificios his in provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis ab officiis &amp; muneribus publicis non excludi, ſed in eo falleris. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus in id latis Pontificiis nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim interdictum eſt, fungi ullis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus ſive adminiſtrationem Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae, ſive Politiam, ſive juſtitiam ſpectent. A militaribus muniis, quantum quidem ego ſcio, excluſi non ſunt, &amp; duriuſculum fuiſſet cum in initiis Reipublicae noſtrae arma ad defendendam publicam libertatem etiam ipſi ſumſerint, ſtrenuamque
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66097:7"/>operam navaverint; eos etiam à militaribus officiis remotos habere, maxime cum ſalus publica nullum inde detrimentum acciperet, tum ob exiguum eorum numerum, tum quod Ordines, naſcentibus omnibus motibus &amp; molitionibus facile ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viam ire potuerint, quod utique tam promptè fieri non potuiſſet, ſi Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificii etiam regimini, muneribus &amp; officiis publicis admoti fuiſſent.</p>
            <p>Certus ſum &amp; liquidò teſtari poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum <hi>Sereniſsimis Principibus</hi> nihil ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què in votis eſſe, quam ut Majeſtas ſua regnet, &amp; qui illi parent, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſibi invicem quam maxime confiſi, ut populus eam obſervet, colat, veneretur, omni ſtudio, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia &amp; obſequio, perſuaſiſſimus ſit de Paterno Majeſtatis ſuae in eum animo &amp; affectu: ſed credere ſeſe &amp; conſcientia ſua convictos eſſe <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Reformatam certiſsimo pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Regnum vero quam</hi> plurimis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis exponi, ſi aut abrogationem <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtae,</hi> uti appellant, aut aliam legum paenalium abolitionem, quam de qua mentionem ſaepius jam feci, promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veant, aut cum Majeſtate ſua id co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66097:8"/>ſe iis conſcientiae vinculis teneri, ſcientes quam ſeveram Deus ab iis rationem exigeret, ſi propter <hi>perituras hujus ſaeculi utilitates</hi> ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram ſuam contuliſſent in ea quae ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcientia animi ſui tam periculoſa tam noxia religioni reformatae exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimant.</p>
            <p>Sereniſſimi Principes maximâ ſemper veneratione proſequuti ſunt &amp; etiamnum proſequuntur Majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſuam, perſuaſi id officii ſui eſſe, tam ex Legis divinae quam natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis praeſcripto; ſed percipere neuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam poſſunt (cum ſic agatur non de ferendis, ſed de abolendis in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Legibus cum conſenſu Regis &amp; populi latis) ab illis exigi poſſe, ut conſentiant tali abrogationi, à qua animus eorum tam alienus eſt, &amp; quae adverſatur omnibus totius orbis Chriſtiani tam Pontificii quam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formati Legibus &amp; conſuetudinibus quae non alios ad regimen, munera &amp; officia publica admittunt, quam qui profitentur religionem publicam &amp; praedominantem, uti ajunt, &amp; quae ſollicitè ſatis praecaverunt, ne ea Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio turbetur aut detrimenti aliquid accipiat.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66097:8"/>
Neceſſe non puto ut multis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruam quâm Sereniſſimi Principes Majeſtati ſuae devoti ſint, cum reipſa id tam publicis documentis, quae quicquid verborum effingi poteſt, longe ſuperant, teſtati, Et parati ſint eadem adhuc pari, aut ſi fieri poſſit, majori ſtudio &amp; zelo repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere.</p>
            <p>Te vero, ut haec quae tantâ cum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate ad te ſcripſi, eodem quo ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta ſunt animo accipias, vehementer rogat.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Vir Nobiliſſime ac Ampliſſime tibi addictiſſimus. GASP: FAGEL.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Pridie Non: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER, Writ by Mijn Heer FAGEL, PENSIONER of HOLLAND, TO Mr. IAMES STEWART, Advocate; Giving an Account of the PRINCE and PRINCESS Of ORANGE's Thoughts concerning the <hi>Repeal</hi> of the TEST, and the PENAL LAWS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am extrem ſorry, that my ill health hath ſo long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred me from Anſwering thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in which you ſo earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know of me, what Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> thoughts are, concerning the Repeal of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and more particularly of that concerning the <hi>Teſt:</hi> I beg you to aſſure your ſelf, that I will deal very plainſy with you in this matter, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout Reſerve, ſince you ſay that your <hi>Letters</hi> were writ by the <hi>King's</hi> knowledg and allowance. I muſt then <hi>firſt</hi> of all aſſure you very poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely, that Their <hi>Highnſſes</hi> have oft en declared, as They did it more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the Marquis of <hi>Albeville,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66097:2"/>His Majeſties <hi>Envoy</hi> Extraordinary to the <hi>States,</hi> that it is Their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>that no Chriſtian ought to be perſecuted for his Conſcience, or be ill uſed becauſe he differs from the publick and eſtablished Religion;</hi> Tnd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, They can <hi>conſent,</hi> that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in <hi>Engeland Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be ſuffered te continue in their <hi>Religion,</hi> with as much Liberty as is allowed them by the <hi>States</hi> in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe <hi>Provinces;</hi> in which it cannot be denied, that they enjoy a full Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience. And as for the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> do not only <hi>conſent,</hi> but do heartily <hi>approve</hi> of their having an entire <hi>Liberty,</hi> for the full exerciſe of their <hi>Religion,</hi> without any trouble or hindrance; ſo that none may be able to give them the leaſt diſturbance upon that account.</p>
            <p>And Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> are very ready, in caſe His Majeſty shall think fit to deſireit, to declare their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to concur in the ſetling, and confirming this Liberty, and as far as it lies in them, they will protect and defend it, and according to the Language of Treaties, They will confirm it with their <hi>Guaranty,</hi> of which you made mention in yours.</p>
            <p>And if his Majeſty shall think fit further to deſire Their concurrence in the Repealing of the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> They are ready to give it; <hi>provided always that thoſe Laws remain ſtill in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66097:2"/>their full vigour, by which the R. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks are shut out of both Houſes of Parliament, and out of all publick Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, Eccleſiaſtical, Civil and Military:</hi> as likewiſe all thoſe other <hi>Laws,</hi> which confirm the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and which ſecures it againſt all the attempts of the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> cannot agree to the Repeal of the <hi>Teſt:</hi> or of thoſe othor <hi>penal Laws</hi> laſt mentioned, that tend to the ſecurity of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion;</hi> ſince the <hi>R. Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> receive no other prejudice from theſe then the being excluded from Parliaments, or from bublick Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments: And that by them the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is covered from all the Deſigns of the <hi>R. Catholicks</hi> againſt it, or againſt the publick tafety; And neither the <hi>Teſt</hi> nor theſe other <hi>Laws</hi> can beſaid to carry in them any ſeverity againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks</hi> upon account of their Conſciences: They are only Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons qualifying men to be Members of Parliament, or to be capable of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Office; by which they muſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare befort God and men, that they are for the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> So hat indeed, all this amounts to no more than a ſecuring the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> from any Prejudices that it may receive from the <hi>R. Catholicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> have thought and dó ſtill think, that more that this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66097:3"/>ought not to be askt, or expected form Them: ſince by this means, the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> and their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity wll be forever ſecured form all trouble in their Perſons or Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or in the Exerciſe of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> and that the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> ought to be ſatisfied with this, and not to diſquet the Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot be admitted to ſit in Parlirment, orto be in Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; or becauſe thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> in which the Security of the <hi>Proteſtant Religiou</hi> does chiefly conſiſt, are not repealed, by which they may be put in a condition to overturn it.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> do alſo believe, that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> wil be fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when tfiey shall be forever co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from all danger of being diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, or punished for the free Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their <hi>Religion,</hi> upon any ſort of pretence what ſoever.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> having declared themſelves ſo poſitive in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, it ſeems very plain to me, that They are far from bring any hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the Freeing <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the Severity of the <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce They are ready to uſe their utmoſt ende avours for the eſtablishing of it: nordo They at all preſs the den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ying to the <hi>R. Catholicks</hi> the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their <hi>Religion,</hi> provided it be managed modeſtly, &amp; with out Pomp or Oſtentation. As for my own part, I ever was and ſtillam
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66097:3"/>very much agaitnſt all thoſe, who would perſecute any <hi>Chriſtian</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he differs from the publick and eſtablished <hi>Religion:</hi> And I hope by the Grace of God to continue ſtill in the ſame mind; for ſince that Light, with which <hi>Religion</hi> illum inates our minds, is according to my ſenſe of things, purely an effect of the Mercy of God to us, we ought then, as I think, to render to God all poſſible Thanks for his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us: and to have Pity for tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe who are ſtill shut up in Error, even as God has pitied us, and to put up moſt earneſt prayers to God, for bringing thoſe into the way of Truth, who ſtray from it, and to uſe all gentle and friendly methods for reducing them to it.</p>
            <p>But I confeſs, I could neyer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how any that profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Chriſtianus,</hi> and that may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their <hi>Religion</hi> freely and witthout any diſturbance, can judge it lawful for them to go about to diſturb the Quiet of any <hi>Kingdom</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> or to verturn Conſtitutions, that ſo they themſelves may be admitted to Employments, and that thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> in which the Security and Quiet of the eſtablished <hi>Religion</hi> conſiſts, should bae shaken.</p>
            <p>It is plain, that the <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> is by the Grace of God and by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, enacted by both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> the pku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66097:4"/>and eſtablished <hi>Religion</hi> both in <hi>Engeland, Sccotland</hi> and <hi>Ireſand;</hi> and that it is provided by thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> that none can be admitted either to a plac-in <hi>Parliament,</hi> or to any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plick Employmene, except thoſe that do openly declare, that they are of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and not <hi>Roman Catholicks;</hi> and it is alſo provided by thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Reeligion</hi> shall be in all time coming ſecured from the Deſigns of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> againſt it: in all whnch I do not ſee, that theſe <hi>Laws</hi> contain any Severity, either againſt the Perſons or Eſtates of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe who cannot take thoſe <hi>Teſts,</hi> that are contrary to the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion;</hi> all the inconveniences that can redound to them from thence, is, that their Perſons, their Eſtates, and even the Exerciſe of their <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> being aſſured to them, only they can have no share in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, nor in Officas of Truſt, as long as their Conſciences do not aliow them to take theſe <hi>Teſt:</hi> and they are not ſuffered to do any thing that is to the prejudice of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since, as I have already told you, Their <hi>Highueſſes</hi> are ready to concur with his <hi>Majeſty</hi> for the Repeal of thoſe <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> by which men are made liable to fines or other Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:66097:4"/>
So I ſee there Remains no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty concerning the Repealing the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> but only this, that ſome would have the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> render'd capable of all publick Truſts and Employments, and that by conſequence, all thoſe should be repealed that have ſecured the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> againſt the deſigns of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> where others at the ſame time are not leſs earneſt to have thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> maintained in their full and due vigour; and think, that the chief Security of the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished <hi>Religion</hi> conſiſts in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of them Sacred and unsha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>It is certain, that there is no <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Common-wealth,</hi> or any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Body or Aſſembly what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in which there are not <hi>Laws</hi> made for the Safety thereof: and that provide againſt all Attempts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, that diſturb thelr peace, and that preſcribe the Conditions and Qualities that they judg neceſſary for all that shall bear Employments in that Kingdom, State or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and no man can pretend, that there is any Injury done him, that he is not admittid to Imployments when he doth not ſatisfie the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Qualities required.</p>
            <p>Nor can it be denied, that there is a great difference to be obſerved
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66097:5"/>in the conduct of the <hi>Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> towards one another: The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> not being ſatisfied to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Reformed</hi> from all places of profit or of Truſt, they do abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſuppreſs the whole Exerciſe of that <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſeverely <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute</hi> all that profeſs it; and this they do in all thoſe places where it is ſafe and without danger, to carry on that rigour. And I am ſorry that we have at this preſent ſo many deplorable Inſtances of this ſeverity before our eyes, that is at the ſame time put in practice in ſo many different pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>I would therefore gladly ſee one ſingle good reaſon to move a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> that fears God, and that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for his <hi>Religion,</hi> to conſent to the Repealing of thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> that have been enacted by the Authority of <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Parliament,</hi> which have no other tendency but to the ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> and to the reſtraining of the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> from a capacity of overturning it; theſe <hi>Laws</hi> inflict neither Fines nor Punishments, and do only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> from a share in the Government, who by being in Employments muſt needs ſtudy to increaſe their Party, and to gain to it mort Credit and Power, which by what we ſee every day, we muſt conclude, will be extreamly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66097:5"/>dangerous to the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> and muſt turn to its great prejudice: ſince in all plases, thoſe that are in publick Employments, do natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Favour that <hi>Religion</hi> of which they are. either more or leſs. And who would go about to perſwade me or agy man elſe to endeavour move Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> whom God hath honoured ſo far as to make them the Protectors of his Church, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of, or to conſent to things ſo hurtful, both to the <hi>Reformed Religion</hi> and to the publick Safety. Nor can I, Sir, with your good leave, in any way grant what you apprehend, That no prejudice will thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to the <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know it is commonly ſaid, that the number of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> in <hi>Engeland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> is very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable; and that they ari poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed only of a very ſmall number of the places of Truſt: tho even as to this, the caſe is quite different in <hi>Ireland:</hi> yet this you muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty grant me, that if their numbers are ſmall, then it is not reaſonable that the publick Peace should be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed on the account of ſo few perſons, eſpecially when ſo great a favour may be offered to them; ſuch as the free Exerciſe of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> would be: and if their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are greater, then there is ſo much the more reaſon to be affraid of them; I do indeed believe that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66097:6"/>
               <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> as things at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtand, will not be very deſirous to be in publick Offices and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, nor that they will make any attempts upon the <hi>Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> both becauſe this is contrary to Law, and becauſe of the great Inconveniences that this may bring at ſome other time both on their Perſons, and their Eſtates: yet if the Reſtraints of the <hi>Law</hi> were once taken off, you would ſee them brought into the Government, and the chief Offices and Places of Truſt would be put in their hands; nor will it be eaſy to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to reſiſt them in this, how ſtedfaſt ſoever he may be; for they will certainly preſs him hard in it, and they will repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this to the <hi>King,</hi> as a matter in which his Conſcience will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; and when they are poſſeſſed of the Publick Offices, what will be left for the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to do, who will find no more the ſupport of the Law, and can expect little Encouragement from ſuch Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates? and on the other hand, the Advantages that the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> would find in being thus ſet looſe from all Reſtrants, are ſo plain, that it were a loſs of time to go about the proving it. I neither can nor will doubt of the ſincerity of his Majeſties intentions, and that he has no other deſign before him in this matter, but that all his Subjects
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66097:6"/>may enjoy in all things the ſame Right and Freedoms.</p>
            <p>But plain Reaſon, as well as the Experience of all Ages, the preſent as well as the paſt, shews, that it will be impoſſible for R. <hi>Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> when they are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed together in places of Truſt and publick Employments, to live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether peaceably, or to maintain a good Correſpondence together. They will be certainly always jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of one another; For the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and the Maxims of both <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions</hi> are ſo oppoſite to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in my opinion I do not ſee how it will be in the power of any Prince or King whatſoever, to keep down thoſe Suſpitions and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities, which will be apt to ariſe upon all occaſions.</p>
            <p>As for that which you apprehend, that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> shall not be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from the <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> that are made againſt the, munleſs at the ſame time the <hi>Teſt</hi> be likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed: this will be indeed a great un happineſs to them; but the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are only to blame for it, who will rather be content that they and their Poſterity shouldl lie ſtill under the weight of the <hi>Pena Laws,</hi> and expoſed to the hatred of the whole Nation; than be ſtill reſtrained from a capacity of attempting any thing againſt the Peace and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66097:7"/>And be deprived of that ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage (if it is at all to be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one) of having ashare in the Government and publick Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſince in all places of the World this has been always the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the <hi>Religion</hi> that is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by Law; and indeed theſe Attempts of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> ought to be ſo much the more ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and guarded againſt by <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> in that they ſee that <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> even when liable to the Severity of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> do yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to per ſwade his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to make the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whether they will or not, diſſolve that Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which they have for their <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:</hi> and to clear a way for brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to the Government, and to publick Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments. in which caſe there would remain no relief for them but what were to be expected from a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>Such then will be very unjuſt to Their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> who shall blame them for any Inconveniency that may ariſe from thence; ſince they have declared themſelves ſo freely on this ſubject, and that ſo much to the advantage even of the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> And ſince the Settlement of matters ſticks at this ſingle point, that Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> cannot be brought to conſent to things that are ſo contrary to <hi>Laws</hi> already in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66097:7"/>being, and that are ſo dangerous and ſo hurtful to the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as the admitting of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to a share in the Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to places of Truſt, and the Repealing of thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> that can have noother effect but the Securing of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> from all the Attempts of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> againſt it would be.</p>
            <p>You write, <hi>That the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks in theſe Provinces are not shut out from Employments and places of Truſt;</hi> But in this you are much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken. For our <hi>Laws</hi> are expreſs, excluding them by name from all share in the Government, and from all Employments either of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy or Juſtice of our Country. It is true, I do not know of any expreſs <hi>Law</hi> that shuts them out of Military Employments, that had indeed been hard, ſince in the firſt Formation of our <hi>State</hi> they jouned with us in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending our publick Liberty, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eminent ſervice during the wars; therefore they were not shut out from thoſe Military Employments; for the publick Safery was no way endanger'd by this, both becauſe their numbers that ſerved in our Troops were not great, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>States</hi> could eaſily prevent any Inconvenience that might ariſe out of that; which could not heve been done ſo eaſily, if the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> had been admitted to a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66097:8"/>Share in the Government, and in the Policy or Juſtice of our <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very certain of this, of which I could give very good proofs, that there is nothing which Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> deſire ſo much, as that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> may Reign happily and in an intire Confidence with his Subjects; and that his ſubjects being perſuaded of his <hi>Majeſtes</hi> fatherly affection to them, may be ready to make him all the returns of duty that are in their Power: But their <hi>High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> are convinced in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that both the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and the Safety of the <hi>Nation,</hi> would be expoſed to moſt certain, Dangers, if either the <hi>Teſt,</hi> or thoſe other <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> of which I have made frequent mention, should be Repealed; <hi>Therefore they cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this, nor concur with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Will; for they believe, they should have much to Anſwer for to God, if the conſideration of any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent advantages should carry them to conſent and concur in things which they believe would be not only dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous but miſchievous to the Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> have ever pay'd a moſt proſound duty to His <hi>Maeſty,</hi> which they will alwayes continue to do; for they conſider themſelves bound to it, both by the Laws of God and of nature; But ſince the matter that is now in hand, relates
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66097:8"/>not to the making of <hi>new Laws,</hi> but to the total Repealing of thoſe alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made both by <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> they do not ſee how it can be expected of them, that they should conſent to ſuch a <hi>Repeal,</hi> to which they have ſo juſt an averſion, as being a thing that is contrary to the Laws and cuſtoms of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>States</hi> whether <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who receive none to a share in the Government, or to publick Employments, but thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the publick and eſtablished <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and that take care to ſecure it againſt all attempts wharſoever.</p>
            <p>I do not think it neceſſary to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate to you how much ther <hi>Highneſſes</hi> are devoted to his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> of which they have given ſuch real Evidences as are beyond all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal ones; and they are Reſolved ſtill to continue in the ſame Duty, and Affection; or rather to encreaſe it, if that is poſſible. I am, SIR,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, &amp;c.</signed>
               <date>Nov. 4. 1687.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London printed in the Year 1688.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66097:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66097:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
